<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hannah Birch</title>
    <description>My content strategy, editing, and production work for the MTA, ProPublica, The Seattle Times, and more.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2020 23:52:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2020 23:52:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.7.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>How To Bring Your Bike On Public Transit</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-bring-your-bike-with-you-on-nyc-public-transit&quot;&gt;How to bring your bike with you on NYC public transit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common question we get about bikes in New York City is if you can take them on the subway. (Yes, you can, but please avoid rush hour.) As the pandemic stretched on in New York and people lined up to buy bicycles, I redesigned and rewrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://new.mta.info/guides/bikes&quot;&gt;the bike page on the MTA site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started by migrating all of the content from the old page onto our new site. I researched rules and guidelines and interviewed co-workers, then rewrote the page. I also included information about non-MTA cycling resources, like the city Department of Transportation’s maps and the Citi Bike bike-share program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/20200805-mta-bike-page-before-after-composite.png&quot; alt=&quot;Two screenshots side-by-side, showing a web page with large photos and organized text, compared to an outdated-looking page that’s mostly text.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The new MTA bike page, left, compared to the old one.&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew I wanted photos that illustrated specific guidelines, like where to stand with your bike on a train and how to get through turnstiles. I worked with MTA photographer Marc Hermann and volunteers from the MTA’s bike-to-work group to art-direct and edit the photos we published on the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new bike page got great feedback from cycling and transportation advocates in the city. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jvhawkins/status/1291065197856202753&quot;&gt;This tweet in particular&lt;/a&gt; utterly made my day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/20200805-mta-bike-page-tweet.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of a tweet reading, ‘This is going to sound kind of dumb, but publishing a page that actually promotes bicycling, includes info on non-MTA modes (ferry, CitiBike), and organizes information so clearly and comprehensively would not have happened a decade ago. MTA comms doing great work.’&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/08/05/how-to-bring-your-bike-on-public-transit.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/08/05/how-to-bring-your-bike-on-public-transit.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Photo Edit For Supported Housing Story</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;living-apart-coming-undone&quot;&gt;Living Apart, Coming Undone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/20181206-supported-housing-lead.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of the opening art of a story, showing a man sitting surrounded by his belongings in his apartment in Flatbush, Brooklyn&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ProPublica reporter Joaquin Sapien spent many months &lt;a href=&quot;https://features.propublica.org/supported-housing/new-york-mentally-ill-housing-group-homes/&quot;&gt;reporting on a program&lt;/a&gt; aimed at helping people with mental illness in New York live on their own. When he filled us in on the living situations of some of the people supervised by this program, we hired &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/george_etheredge/?hl=en&quot;&gt;George Etheredge&lt;/a&gt;, a freelance photographer, to document the visual side of the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;inset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/20181206-supported-housing-3-up.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Screenshot of some of George Etheredge’s photos in the layout.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to keen reporting skills, we loved George’s ability to capture people’s unraveling lives in a way that still felt respectful and humane. I felt a sharp contrast in the photo edit: We had a photo set documenting shocking living situations (a liquifying cantaloupe, a shower left running for the “oxygen,”), but wanted to show them in a way that didn’t make the images feel gratuitous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was continually thinking about how to use the evidentiary photographs as a way of holding the system accountable, without compromising the dignity and humanity of the people we photographed. (George’s thoughtful portraits went a long way here.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://features.propublica.org/supported-housing/new-york-mentally-ill-housing-group-homes/&quot;&gt;Read the story.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We co-published the story with The New York Times and Frontline, and we’re working on a documentary with Frontline slated to debut in early 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 06 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/12/06/photo-edit-for-supported-housing-story.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/12/06/photo-edit-for-supported-housing-story.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Electionland 2018</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;covering-access-to-the-vote-in-real-time&quot;&gt;Covering access to the vote in real time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/20181106-electionland.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Electionland newsroom&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.propublica.org/electionland/&quot;&gt;Electionland&lt;/a&gt; is a collaborative ProPublica project that covers voting, nationally and in real time. We partnered with newsrooms across the country, built a database of reliable, vetted tips and identified election administration problems in enough time for them to be addressed on Election Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;inset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/20181106-electionland-team.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;From left: David Sleight, Jillian Kumagai, me and Setareh Baig, in the Electionland newsroom on Nov. 6. (📸: Mike Tigas)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was the main production contact for Electionland 2018, working with the Electionland team, the design and production team and ProPublica editors to make sure training, preparation and day-of logistics went smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CUNY’s graduate school of journalism graciously let us use their newsroom on Election Day for this project. We tried to anticipate as many needs as we could, from thinking about training and publishing workflows to ethernet dongles and desks. I also hired a freelance photographer, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.erinlefevre.com/#1&quot;&gt;Erin Lefevre&lt;/a&gt;, to document the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Election Day was one of our highest-volume publishing days of the year. We had four design and production team members onsite all day to produce stories, handle art research and help keep the site running well. I don’t often get to produce live, breaking news, so I loved the throwback to my daily-newsroom days. (And yes, there was pizza.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/06/electionland-2018.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/11/06/electionland-2018.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Illustration Commission For Heart Transplant Series</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;heart-failure&quot;&gt;Heart Failure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;inset&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/20180516-heart-failure.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of the opening art of a story, showing an illustration of a pair of hands stitching a heart with medical instruments nearby&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charlie Ornstein at ProPublica and Mike Hixenbaugh at the Houston Chronicle spent 2018 reporting on the heart transplant program at St. Luke’s, a hospital in Houston with a renowned reputation, and why the program’s complications rates were so high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We brought &lt;a href=&quot;http://pepmontserrat.com/&quot;&gt;Pep Montserrat&lt;/a&gt; onboard to illustrate the first few stories, augmenting the art the Houston Chronicle shot and shared with us. We wanted to allude to the systemwide problems in addition to showing people who had been affected by the problems. Illustration helped us do that. We loved Pep’s approach to the subject matter, his mix of literal and figurative heart shapes and the texture he added.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.propublica.org/series/heart-failure/&quot;&gt;See the series.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 May 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/05/16/illustration-commission-for-heart-transplant-series.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/05/16/illustration-commission-for-heart-transplant-series.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Google Privacy Illo</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;google-is-watching-you&quot;&gt;Google is watching you.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/20161021-google-privacy-630x420.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Google logo with eyeballs instead of O's&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made this illustration to go with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.propublica.org/article/google-has-quietly-dropped-ban-on-personally-identifiable-web-tracking&quot;&gt;Julia Angwin story&lt;/a&gt; about Google dropping its ban on personally identifiable web tracking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This took all of about three minutes to put together. Sometimes you have to sweat over ideas for an illustration … and sometimes they just stroll into your head fully formed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/10/21/google-privacy-illo.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/10/21/google-privacy-illo.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My Story As A Dmv Edge Case</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-story-as-a-dmv-edge-case-how-to-battle-bureaucracy-and-win&quot;&gt;My Story as a DMV Edge Case: How to Battle Bureaucracy and Win&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I showed up with paperwork for my low-vision condition, the DMV was totally baffled. Here’s how I walked them through an edge case and how you can use the strategies yourself. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.propublica.org/article/my-story-as-a-dmv-edge-case-how-to-battle-bureaucracy-and-win&quot;&gt;Read the full story.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/02/18/my-story-as-a-dmv-edge-case.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/02/18/my-story-as-a-dmv-edge-case.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Please Stop Calling Me A Guru</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;please-stop-calling-me-a-guru&quot;&gt;Please stop calling me a guru.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Journalism has, in my experience, had a difficult time figuring out what to call the people filling the technology centric jobs that didn’t exist a decade ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pro tip: Guru is not a good option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve heard “news producer.” I’ve heard “homepage producer,” “content editor,” “social media editor,” and “Web editor.” I’ve been called a handful of those, with “Web producer” being the current iteration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often get confused head tips from people who aren’t journalists — and people who are journalists — when they ask what I do. That’s OK. I don’t mind explaining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a dangerous trend has emerged among other journalists. I see it happening during formal introductions or meetings, when someone is trying to communicate what I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a moment of grasping for the right word — “producer” doesn’t mean much to people outside the industry — and too often, that word is “guru.”
Every time that happens, I cringe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calling me a “guru” is a cop out. The last thing I want to do is give people who don’t understand my job an excuse to continue to do so, and that’s exactly what such a mystical titles does. The word conjures feelings of magic ponies and rainbows without saying anything about my actual skillset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Producer” is not as immediately descriptive as “photo editor” or “art director,” but it still connotes a refined set of responsibilities.
 Production is a job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand the instinct. “Guru” feels complimentary and edgy, not unlike Google’s ninjas, and it rings of Webby-ness. But it fundamentally fails as a job description.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not a guru. I have a highly technical job that requires skills that should be described in language that communicates expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Reporter” and “editor,” for example, do that. And there is a hierarchy built into how most newsrooms are structured: There are senior reporters, section editors, managing editors, editors in chief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chain of command for Web work is less standardized and more malleable. As a producer, I’ve reported to lead news producers, digital managing editors, design directors and even, indirectly, a copy-desk chief-slash-standard editor, whatever that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I get it. The organization of the Web world in the context of a newsroom is fairly new, and people don’t always know what to call things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please call me a producer. I swear I will patiently explain my job as often as needed. Because after years of doing this, I’ve realized the only way to make my title more familiar is to use it more often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Post-publication edit (hat-tip to Terry Parris Jr.). This post in a nutshell: https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=KgmO32IdwuE]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2015/06/27/please-stop-calling-me-a-guru.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2015/06/27/please-stop-calling-me-a-guru.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Illustration For Municipal Internet Explainer</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;vector-illustration-for-municipal-internet-explainer&quot;&gt;Vector illustration for municipal Internet explainer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/20150123-internet-access-630x420.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;An illustration showing a cityscape with an internet cord alongside the buildings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used Sketch.app and Photoshop to create this vector illustration for a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.propublica.org/article/obama-wants-you-to-have-cheap-fast-internet-but-many-cities-arent-allowed-t&quot;&gt;ProPublica story&lt;/a&gt; about municipal Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2015/01/23/illustration-for-municipal-internet-explainer.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2015/01/23/illustration-for-municipal-internet-explainer.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Best Of The Northwest</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-of-the-northwest-ceo-pay&quot;&gt;Best of the Northwest, CEO Pay&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;inset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/20140621-best-northwest-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of a story with a sidebar with graphics&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our digital team put together a revamped version of Best of the Northwest, The Seattle Times’ annual ranking of publicly traded Northwest companies. The roundup included a highly sortable chart, put together by a newsroom developer, and an interactive landing page, spearheaded by the same developer and our lead digital producer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I helped design story-level packaging for Best of the Northwest, incorporating nuances from the print design and other parts of the project. I also built out homepage packages for each piece, keeping an eye on traffic and engagement time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;inset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/20140621-best-northwest-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of a story with a sidebar with graphics&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our yearly look at what local CEOs got paid ran a week after Best of the Northwest. This was less labor intensive for our developer because &lt;a href=&quot;http://seattletimes.com/html/localpages/2023892102_ceo-pay-2014.html&quot;&gt;the accompanying chart&lt;/a&gt; wasn’t as robust. However, it was challenging to make the print design elements translate to the web. I designed and built out &lt;a href=&quot;http://seattletimes.com/html/businesstechnology/2023899334_ceopaymainxml.html&quot;&gt;a sidebar&lt;/a&gt; that accompanied each of the nine stories in the section, pulling in the big illustration from print and making sure other important elements were surfaced. And I coordinated with editors on homepage play.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2014/06/21/best-of-the-northwest.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2014/06/21/best-of-the-northwest.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Oso Mudslide</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;breaking-news-coveage-oso-mudslide&quot;&gt;Breaking news coveage: Oso mudslide&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;inset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/20140322-mudslide.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of a story with a photo of a mudslide&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was the only producer in the building on Saturday, March 22, when I saw tweets from a PIO with the sheriff’s office that there was a house in the road after a mudslide near Darrington. I worked with a metro editor to assess the scale of the slide, updating our social media accounts and the homepage as we got information. I realized this was by far the biggest story I’d worked on, at the Times or elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next two weeks were a blur. The digital team worked long, harried hours keeping the website updated with the work produced by more than 30 reporters and countless editors and managers. We had &lt;a href=&quot;http://seattletimes.com/html/localnews/2023218573_mudslidewarningsxml.html&quot;&gt;watchdog stories&lt;/a&gt; running within days of the slide. We built a hugely popular &lt;a href=&quot;http://seattletimes.com/flatpages/local/interactivebeforeandafterthe530mudslide.html&quot;&gt;before-and-after interactive&lt;/a&gt; that was the centerpiece on SeattleTimes.com for the better part of a day. We put together a &lt;a href=&quot;http://seattletimes.com/flatpages/local/victimsoftheosomudslide.html&quot;&gt;page memorializing victims&lt;/a&gt; of the slide. We had too many daily stories and blog posts to count, tracking updates as search efforts continued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirty-one reporters contributed to a &lt;a href=&quot;http://seattletimes.com/html/localnews/2023259205_mudslidenarrativexml.html&quot;&gt;narrative of the events that day&lt;/a&gt;, a story with a custom layout I hand coded late one night. We used social media to tell readers what we knew and how to get help. We lowered our paywall on resources for victims of the mudslide. (Read editor Kathy Best’s thoughts on that in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.poynter.org/latest-news/mediawire/246699/why-the-seattle-times-lowered-its-paywall-during-the-mudslide-but-didnt-suspend-it/&quot;&gt;this Poynter piece&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was exhausting in many ways, but it’s impossible to work on a story like this and not see the significance journalism has. &lt;a href=&quot;http://seattletimes.com/flatpages/local/oso-mudslide-coverage.html&quot;&gt;See all coverage of the Oso mudslide.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2014/03/22/oso-mudslide.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2014/03/22/oso-mudslide.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
